07 - Future Tasks of the Alliance - “Harmel Report”
NATO Archives Online
- Report by Sub-group 4 Developments in Regions outside the NATO area (April 1967 – October 1967), 1967-04 - 1967-10; Volume 7; 25 Items
  - First meeting of Sub-group 4 “Developments in Regions outside the NATO area” held on 18 April 1967, Section 1
    - Meeting of Sub-group 4 on 18 April 1967 – Record of the discussion. (April 1967) ENG 1
    - Summary to Secretary General of the first meeting of Sub-group 4 of the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance on 18 April 1967 (19 April 1967) ENG 1
    - SG(67)145. Summary of first meeting of Sub-group 4 (19 April 1967) FRE 1
    - SG(67)147. Decision sheet of first meeting of Sub-group 4 on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (20 April 1967) FRE 1
    - Report by Professor Patijn to the first meeting of Sub-group 4. (April 1967) ENG 1
  - Progress report by the rapporteur of Sub-Group 4 established after the first meeting, Section 2
    - Memorandum by Secretary of the sub-group to Professor Patijn on progress report to the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (25 April 1967) ENG 1
    - AC/261-D/2. Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Progress Report by the Rapporteur of Sub-group 4, C.L. Patijn (12 May 1967) BIL 1
  - Second meeting of Sub-Group 4 held on 23 May, 1967, Section 3
    - ED(67)38. Mémo du Directeur des Affaires Economiques au Secrétaire général adjoint pour les Affaires Politiques: Contribution au Sous-groupe no.4 sur les tâches futures de l’Alliance. (9 May 1967) FRE 1
    - No. 2953. Netherlands Delegation. Letter circulating the introduction of the draft report by rapporteur Professor. Patijn. (11 May 1967) ENG 1
    - No. 2953 II. Netherlands Delegation. Letter enclosing Part II of Draft Report by Prof. Patijn. (12 may 1967) ENG 1
    - Draft Report of Professor Patijn, Rapporteur of Sub-group 4. (19 May 1967) ENG 1
    - Report by the Secretary of Sub-group 4 to the Secretary General on second meeting of Sub-group 4 on developments in regions outside the NATO area.. (24 May 1967) ENG 1
  - Report on visit to United States and Canada by the rapporteur of Sub-Group 4, Mr. Patijn and by Mr. Vernon, 4th-10th June, 1967, Section 4
    - DPA(67)138. Political Affairs Division. Memo from Assistant Secretary General for Political Affairs to the Financial Controller on the mission to Washington and Ottawa (26 May 1967) ENG 1
    - JV(67)287. Report by John Vernon on the visit by the Rapporteur to Washington D.C., Ottawa and New York, 4th-10th June, 1967. (12 June 1967) ENG. Annex: Records of meetings held during the visit. (June 1967) ENG 1
    - JV(67)314. Report from John Vernon to the Director of Information on the trip to Washington and Ottawa (22 June 1967) ENG 1
    - DI(67)315. Director of Information. Memo to the Private Office on Mr. Vernon and Mr. Patijn visit to the United States and Canada (4 July 1967) ENG 1
  - Third meeting of Sub-Group 4 held on 29th June, 1967, Section 5
    - F/7250/67. Memo from the rapporteur to the members of Sub-group 4 with suggestions for improving the political consultation in NATO.. (23 June 1967) ENG 1
    - F/7249/67. Draft new section by the rapporteur to the members of the sub-group 2 on “Reflections on the Rôle of NATO in World Affairs” (23 June 1967) ENG 1
    - Summary report on the third meeting of Sub-group 4 by the Secretary of Sub-group 4 to the Secretary General. (30 June 1967) ENG 1
  - Mr. Jaenicke’s note to Professor Patijn on the origin and development of APAG, Regional Experts’ Committee and POLADS, Section 6
    - RS(67)90. Report on an African Interlude from W.M. Newton to the Assistant Secretary General Political Affairs (11 July 1976) ENG 1
    - DPA(67)169. Political Affairs Division. Notes by the Assistant Secretary General (Political Affairs) on the Atlantic Policy Advisory Group, committees of experts from capitals and POLADS. (20 July 1967) ENG 1
  - Fourth meeting of Sub-Group 4 held on 14 September, 1967, Section 7
    - No. 5276. Netherlands Delegation. Letter to the Secretary General enclosing draft report by Prof. Patijn (F9525/67) for discussion in the next meeting (31 August 1967) ENG 1
    - SQS(67)105 Doc. F 9525/67. Political Affairs, Special Question Section. Note by M. de Camaret to ASG Political Affairs (4 September 1967) FRE 1
    - Summary report of the fourth meeting of sub-group 4 to the Secretary General. (September 1967) ENG 1
    - No. 6001. Netherlands Delegation. Letter to Secretary General enclosing final version of report by Prof. Patijn. (F/10748/67) (5 October 1967) ENG 1
- Interim Report to June 1967 Ministerial meeting in Luxembourg and further discussions. (May 1967 – November 1967), 1967-05 - 1967-11; Volume 8; 55 Items
  - Interim Report to Ministers in Luxembourg, June 1967, prepared by the Special Group, Section 1
    - AC/261-N/8. Special Group on the Future Task of the Alliance. Note listing meetings on 18, 19 and 23 May 1967 of the Special Group, Rapporteurs and Sub-Groups for the two weeks following Whitsun. (12 May 1967) BIL 1
    - AC/261-A/1. Special Group on the Future Task of the Alliance. Agenda of the meeting to be held at the Permanent Headquarters, Paris on Friday 19th May, 1967. (12 May 1967) BIL 1
    - AC/261-A/1(Revised). Special Group on the Future Task of the Alliance. Agenda of the meeting to be held at the Permanent Headquarters, Paris on Friday 19th May, 1967. (12 May 1967) BIL 1
    - Draft passage for the Ministerial Communique Relative to the Exercise of the Future Tasks of the Alliance (17 May 1967) ENG 1
    - Draft Progress Report of the Council to Ministers Meeting at Luxembourg Relative to the Exercise on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (17 May 1967) ENG 1
    - Interim Report of the Council to Ministers Meeting at Luxembourg Relative to the Studies on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (19 May 1967) ENG 1
    - Summary record of the meeting held on 19 May 1967 by the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance to discuss and prepare the “progress report for eventual submission to ministers” (May 1967). ENG+FRE 1
    - Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Memo from Deputy Executive Secretary to Secretary General with a summary record of meeting held on 19th May 1967. (24 May 1967) ENG 1
    - Report of the meeting of rapporteurs of Sub-Groups of the Special Group on Future Tasks of the Alliance, under the Chairmanship of the Secretary General. (19 May 1967) ENG 1
    - AC/261-A/2. Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Agenda for the meeting to be held at the Permanent Headquarters Paris on Monday, 29th May, 1967. (22 May, 1967) BIL 1
    - Submission by Deputy Executive Secretary to Secretary General of draft agenda for the meeting of the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance on 29th May 1967. (22 May 1967) ENG 1
    - FCM(67)82. Memo from F.C. Menne, Deputy Executive Secretary to Mr. C. Chapman Redrafting the interim report to Ministers on Future Tasks of the Alliance (22 May 1967) ENG 1
    - No. 237 Délégation Française auprès de l’OTAN. Observations concernant la préparation du rapport intérimaire au Secrétaire Général. (22 May 1967) FRE 1
    - United States Delegation. Letter from US Permanent Representative, Harlan Cleveland to Secretary General following a meeting of the Special Group on the Study of the Future of the Alliance. (22 May 1967) ENG 1
    - FCM(67)84. Memo from F.C. Menne to Mr. C. Chapman on redraft of interim report to ministers on Future Tasks of the Alliance. (24 May 1967) ENG 1
    - AC/261-D/3. Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Draft interim report by the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance to the Council in ministerial session. (25 May 1967) FRE 1
    - AC/261-D/3. Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance – Draft interim report by the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance to the Council in ministerial session. (25 May 1967) ENG 1
    - DPA(67)142. Political Affairs Division. US proposal to Secretary General for new wording of paragraph 11 of draft interim report. (29 May 1967) ENG 1
    - AC/261-D/3. Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Draft interim report by the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance to the Council in ministerial session. (25 May 1967) FRE 1
    - AC/261-D/3. Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance – Draft interim report by the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance to the Council in ministerial session. (25 May 1967) ENG 1
    - DPA(67)142. Political Affairs Division. US proposal to Secretary General for new wording of paragraph 11 of draft interim report. (29 May 1967) ENG 1
    - Brief for the Secretary General for the meeting of the Special Group. (29 May 1967) ENG 1
    - C-M(67)33. Council Memorandum. Interim report by the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance to the Council in ministerial session. (30 May 1967) FRE 1
    - C-M(67)33. Council Memorandum. Interim report by the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance to the Council in ministerial session. (30 May 1967) ENG 1
    - Brief for the Secretary General for the Meeting of the Special Group (30 May 1967) ENG 1
    - C-R(67)24. NATO Council meeting on 31 May 1967. Extract on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. ( 8 June 1967) BIL 1
    - C-R(67)29. NATO Council meeting on 14 June 1967. Extract on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (10 July 1967) BIL 1
    - Note for the file drafted by Archives Section. ENG 1
  - Discussions with Permanent Representatives (12th and 24th July) and in Bonn (Königswinter) (21st July) with rapporteurs on the manner in which the Harmel’s Exercise may unfold in future – Schedule of work of the Four Sub-Groups and the Special Group, Section 2
    - Future Tasks of the Alliance – Dates and submission of reports and meetings of Sub-Groups. ENG 1
    - GAS(67)74. Political Affairs Division General Affairs Section. Memorandum to Assistant Secretary General for Political Affairs from C.A. Chapman on his meeting with the Secretary General (11 July 1967) ENG 1
    - DPA(67)159. Political Affairs Division. Memorandum to the Secretary General from the Assistant Secretary General for Political Affairs on the Future Task of the Alliance and the schedule of work for the four sub-groups. (12 July 1967) ENG 1
    - Record of a private meeting of Permanent Representatives held on 12 July 1967 on the Harmel Exercise.(July 1967) ENG 1
    - Draft Paper. Analysis of tendencies revealed in the discussion of Permanent Representatives on 12th July, 1967. (17 July 1967) ENG 1
    - DPA(67)163. Political Affairs Division. Report from the Assistant Secretary General for Political Affairs to the Secretary General on the analysis of tendencies revealed in the discussion of Permanent Representatives on 12th July 1967. (18 July 1967) ENG
    - United Kingdom Delegation. Draft by Adam Watson on suggestions for basic ideas underlying the papers of all rapporteurs. (17 July 1967) ENG 1
    - United States Delegation. Memorandum for Rapporteurs by Foy D. Kohler, Deputy Under Secretary of State on Future of the Alliance Study sent to the Secretary General. (18 July 1967) ENG 1
    - DPA(67)166. Political Affairs Division. Report to the Secretary General from the Assistant Secretary General for Political Affairs on the Future Tasks of the Alliance and the future procedure. (19 July 1967) ENG 1
    - Record of Meeting of Rapporteurs of Sub-groups of Special Group on Future tasks of the Alliance in Köningswinter, on 21st July and the list of participants. (25 July 1967) ENG 1
    - PO(67)559. Private Office. Rapport du Secrétaire général au Groupe Special, sur la réunion des Rapporteurs qui a eu lieu à Koeningswinter, Allemagne, le 21 Juillet 1967. (4 August 1967) FRE 1
    - PO(67)559. Private Office. Report by the Secretary General to the Special Group on the meeting of Rapporteurs at Koeningswinter, Germany, on 21st July 1967. (4 August 1967) ENG 1
    - Record of the Private Meeting on 24th July 1967, of Permanent Representatives of countries furnishing Harmel exercise rapporteurs. (24 July 1967) ENG 1
    - Record of the private meeting on 24th July 1967, of Permanent Representatives of countries furnishing Harmel exercise rapporteurs – Short version. (24 July 1967) ENG 1
    - No. 2122. Belgian Delegation. Outline of the general report. (31 July 1967) ENG+FRE 1
    - PO(67)580. Private Office. Letter to M. Spaak from J.A. Roberts. (3 August 1967) FRE 1
    - PO(67)583 to 587. Private Office. Letters from J.A. Roberts to Permanent Representatives of delegations writing of an enclosed copy of Mr. Spaak’s outline for the report to ministers of the Special Group. (3 August 1967) ENG+FRE 1
    - United Kingdom Delegation. Letter to Mr. Roberts informing him of the forwarding of his letter, PO(67)585 to Mr. Watson. (4 August 1967) ENG 1
    - Record of conversation between the Secretary General, Mr. Rostow and Mr. Cleveland. (10 September 1967) ENG 1
    - DPA(67)192. Political Affaires Division. Distribution of reports by rapporteurs to Political Affairs Division. (15 and 19 September 1967) FRE 1
    - GAS(67)95. Political Affairs Division, General Affairs Section. Future work programme of the Council for the exercise on the Future Tasks of the Alliance (18 September 1967) ENG 1
    - C-R(67)39. NATO Council meeting on 20 September 1967. Extract on future programme of work for the Council on Future Tasks of the Alliance. (2 October 1967) BIL 1
  - Circulation of Reports of the four Sub-Groups, Section 3
    - AC/261-N/13. Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Provision of additional texts. Reports of the four sub-groups in the AC/261 series sent to certain delegations from F.C. Menne, Deputy Executive Secretary. (2 November 1967) ENG+ FRE 1
    - AC/261-N/13(Revised). Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. Provision of Additional Texts. Reports of the four sub-groups in the AC/261 series sent to certain delegations from F.C. Menne, Deputy Executive Secretary. (16 November 1967) ENG+FRE
    - PB(67)119. Memo by P. De Burlet, Staff Officer (Political Affairs Division) to Deputy Executive Secretary on report by rapporteur of sub-group 2. (21 November 1967) FRE 1
    - Note pour M. Synadinos par le Chef de la Section des Archives. (23 June 1992) FRE 1
    - EXS(92)150. Executive Secretariat. Release of NATO Information: Corrigendum to one of the sub-group reports covered by the request for release contained in PO(92)105. (2 July 1992) BIL 1
- Approval of Final Report during December 1967 Council Ministerial Session in Brussels. (October 1967 – December 1967), 1967-10 - 1967-12; Volume 9; 74 Items
  - Summary and Analysis of Rapporteurs’ Reports by the Political Division, Section 1
    - DPA(67)206. Political Affairs Division. Analysis from the Assistant Secretary General for Political Affairs to the Secretary General of the reports to be submitted by the rapporteurs of the sub-groups of the Special Group. (2 October 1967) ENG 1
    - DPA(67)207. Political Affairs Division. Summary from the Assistant Secretary General for Political Affairs to the Secretary General on the different matters which have been dealt with in each of the four reports on the Future Tasks of the Alliance (2 Octo
  - Meeting with rapporteurs of sub-groups at Ditchley Park on 11th October to review and compare the findings of the reports and private meeting of Permanent Representatives on 18th October to examine the future procedural aspects of the study, Section 2
    - DPA(67)213. Political Affairs Division. Record of meeting between the Secretary General and the German Foreign Minister at the Foreign Office, Bonn. (9 October 1967) ENG 1
    - Record of meeting of rapporteurs of Sub-Groups for study on Future Tasks of the Alliance. (11 October 1967) ENG 1
    - Sommaire des rapports sur les Tâches Futures de l’Alliance projet. (11 October 1967) FRE 1
    - Draft Summary of reports on Future Tasks of the Atlantic Alliance. (9 October 1967) ENG 1
    - Letter from the British Foreign Office with attached draft report to the members of the Special Group. (11 October 1967) ENG 1
    - PO(67)770. Private Office. Projet de Synthèse des Rapports sur les Tâches Futures de l’Alliance. (18 October 1967) FRE 1
    - PO(67)770. Private Office. Draft Summary of rapporteurs’ reports on Future Tasks of the Atlantic Alliance. (18 October 1967) ENG 1
    - PO(67)769. Private Office. Le nouvel horaire pour la réunion du Conseil - Le 18 Octobre 1967. (16 October 1967) FRE 1
    - PO(67)769. Private Office. The new timetable for the Council meeting – 18th October 1967. (16 October 1967) ENG 1
    - Brief for a meeting for the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (18 October 1967) ENG 1
    - Summary record of a private meeting of Permanent Representatives from the Deputy Executive Secretary to the Secretary General. (18 October 1967) ENG 1
    - 20-02-5/3623/67 geh. German Delegation.. Letter from German Minister of Foreign Affairs to Secretary General following the meeting held on 9th October 1967 in Bonn relating to possible French adverse reactions as regard to the Future Tasks of the Alliance
  - Private meeting of Permanent Representatives on 25th October to prepare the meeting of the special Group of 7th November, and, subsequent circulation by the Secretary General of a list of issues to be discussed, Section 3
    - DPA/67/218. Political Affairs Division. Memo from the Assistant Secretary General for Political Affairs to the Secretary General on Future Tasks of the Alliance: Study of the issues in the Harmel Exercise. (20 October 1967) ENG 1
    - Draft working paper with list of points to be discussed by the high-level meeting of the Special Group. (26 October 1967) ENG 1
    - Summary record of a private meeting of Permanent Representatives held on Wednesday, 25th October from Deputy Executive Secretary to Secretary General. (26 October 1967) ENG 1
    - PO(67)796. Private Office. Liste des questions à discuter par le Groupe spécial réuni a un échelon élevé. (30 October 1967) FRE 1
    - PO(67)769. Private Office. List of issues to be discussed by the high level meeting of the Special Group from the Secretary General to the Permanent Representatives. (30 October 1967) ENG 1
  - Soviet comments on the Harmel’s Exercise, Section 4
    - RS(67)124. Report on Soviet comment on the Harmel Exercise and NATO (26 October 1967) ENG 1
  - Position of the French Representative on the Harmel Exercise, Section 5
    - SPA(67)1. Special Advisor for Policy Planning. Report to the ASG Political Affairs on the position of the French Representatives on the Harmel Exercise. (14 November 1967) ENG 1
  - Meeting of the Secretary General with Panel Group from US Association from the United Nations on 15th November, Section 6
    - Summary record of a meeting of the Secretary General with panel group from United States Association from the United Nations. (15 November 1967) ENG 1
  - Meeting of the Special Group held on 7/8th November, and, circulation of a draft report for submission to the Special Group on 22nd November by the Secretary General, Section 7
    - Canadian Delegation. Letter of attendance from Canadian Ambassador and Permanent Representative to Secretary General regarding the meeting of the Special Group on 7th November. (2 November 1967) ENG 1
    - Italian Delegation. Letter of attendance to Secretary General regarding the meeting of the Special Group on 7th November. (3 November 1967) FRE 1
    - Draft of Introductory remarks by the Secretary General for the meeting of Tuesday, 7th November 1967. (November 1967) ENG 1
    - Statement made by US Under Secretary Eugene Rostow on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (November 1967) ENG 1
    - Speaking Notes for the United Kingdom Representative on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (November 1967) ENG 1
    - Statement by Turkish Representative on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (November 1967) ENG 1
    - Statement of Norwegian Representative M. Jacobsen on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (November 1967) FRE 1
    - F 12032/67. Statement by the Netherlands Representative on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (November 1967) ENG 1
    - Statement by Netherlands Representative Mr. de Ranitz on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (7 November 1967) ENG 1
    - Italian Delegation. Déclaration faite par l’Ambassadeur de Ferrariis Salzano au Groupe Spécial. (7 November 1967) FRE 1
    - Statement by Greek Representative on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (November 1967) FRE 1
    - Statement by German Representative on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (November 1967) ENG 1
    - Statement by French Representative on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (7 November 1967) FRE 1
    - Statement by French Representative on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (8 November 1967) FRE 1
    - Statement by Danish Representative on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (November 1967) FRE 1
    - AC/261-R. Statement by Canadian Representative (November 1967). ENG+FRE 1
    - Statement by Belgian Representative on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (6 November 1967) FRE 1
    - Italian Delegation. Opinion of Italian authorities on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (13 November 1967) FRE 1
    - Belgian Ministry of Foreign Affairs. Letter from Pierre Harmel to Secretary General commenting on a meeting of the Special Group. (13 November 1967) FRE 1
    - PO(67)836. Reply by the Secretary General to the letter sent by Pierre Harmel on 13th November. (16 November 1967) FRE 1
    - Draft notes by Denmark and Norway on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. (November 1967) ENG 1
    - Draft report on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. ENG 1
    - Draft report on the Future Tasks of the Alliance. ENG 1
    - Draft report number 3 on the Future Tasks of the Alliance for submission to the Special Group on 22nd November 1967. (14 November 1967) ENG 1
    - Draft reports of the Special Group. ENG 1
    - PO(67)832. Draft report for submission to the Special Group on 22nd November, 1967. (16 November 1967) FRE 1
    - PO(67)832. Draft report for submission to the Special Group on 22nd November, 1967. (16 November 1967) ENG 1
  - Meeting of the Special Group on 22nd November, leading to Draft Report to Council in Ministerial session, Section 8
    - ASG(PA). Assistant Secretary General Political Affairs. Draft Report for submission to the Special Group on 22nd November 1967 with amendments by various countries. (November 1967) ENG 1
    - MJ(67)164. Letter from the Secretary Political Committee to the Director of Private Office regarding participants to the Special Group meeting of 22nd November. (23 November 1967) ENG 1
    - Brief for the Secretary General for the meeting of the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance, 22nd November 1967. (November 1967) ENG 1
    - Summary of the discussion of the Special Group on 22nd November 1967 concerning the report submitted by the Secretary General. (November 1967) ENG 1
    - C-M(67). Draft Council Memorandum report by the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance to the Council in Ministerial Session. (24 November 1967) BIL 1
  - On 13th December, 1967, Council in Ministerial Session Approved the Report on the Future Tasks of the Alliance as Amended During Discussion and Subsequently Issued as C-M(67)74 (2nd Revise) – Known as Harmel Report, Section 9
    - C-M(67)74. Report by the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance to the Council in ministerial session. (28 November 1967) FRE 1
    - C-M(67)74. Report by the Special Group on the Future Tasks of the Alliance to the Council in ministerial session (28 November 1967) ENG 1
    - RS(67)133. Political Affairs Division, Research Section. Report on the Future Tasks of the Alliance from W.M Newton to Assistant Secretary General, Political Affairs. (28 November 1967) ENG 1